So on meetings, there's a requirement that the
board meets quarterly to deliberate on the affairs
of the business and directors are expected to
attend at least two-thirds of those meetings
to qualify for re-election.
Directors are also expected to sit and serve
on board committees and the codes and the
respective guidelines also define the kinds of committees
that the board should have.
I discussed conflicts of interest earlier on, this
is also a code provision and the codes
are required and the guidelines as well that
directors should not just abstain from discussions but
should also recuse themselves, meaning that they should
exit meetings where they have conflicts of interest.
There's a requirement on auditors as well, of
course, I mean each organisation will appoint auditors
but they are not supposed to serve for
10 years consecutively after which they retire and
then serve a pull-off period of five
years following which they can be reappointed.
There's a requirement also that the board should
have a remuneration policy.
The remuneration policy should determine and define the
kind of remuneration that directors are entitled to
but this is strictly speaking restricted to seasonal
allowance and directors fees as well as reimbursable
expenses including travel and hotel expenses.
To mention here that sometimes you find that
directors earn other remuneration.
Strictly speaking, this is not in consonance with
the expectations of the code and the respective
guidelines.
Again, for the sake of emphasis, remuneration is
limited or should be limited to directors fees,
seasonal allowance and other reimbursable expenses.
Of course, directors are also entitled to periodic
training which could be local training, could be
international training but there should be a training
policy that allows directors to be exposed to
periodic training and new directors are expected also
to have an induction not just into the
business of the company but also into the
roles and responsibilities of the director.
Every company should have a company secretary and
the responsibilities of the company secretary are clearly
stated in the respective codes and guidelines but
to just mention here that the office of
the company secretary is rated almost as highly
as that of a director by the respective
codes and guidelines.
The appointment of the company secretary is a
board level appointment so is the removal of
the company secretary so management cannot remove or
appoint a company secretary without the authorisation of
the board.
To also mention that the company secretary reports
to the board and not to management.
There's a dotted line reporting to the CEO
or to the managing director by the company
secretary but this is only related to administrative
matters, functionally the company secretary reports or should
report to the board through the board chair.